[SPEAKER_00]: I have a question.
[SPEAKER_00]: Go ahead.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about how to be self-reliant when there are many dhamma teachers all claiming, essentially, their own technique, view, process.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the way that one can become self-reliant before right view?
[SPEAKER_05]: No.
[SPEAKER_05]: Self-reliance starts with the right view.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's the... that's the peril of putridionous situation.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, yeah, that's why you have to be extra careful and extra careful, extra honest, extra transparent.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you're not... you're not acting out of mere preferences.
[SPEAKER_05]: But actually, like, sound reasoning, using your intelligence to discern, and knowing that for as long as you are not self-reliant, well, you should not entirely rely on somebody else and take for granted.
[SPEAKER_05]: But everything has to be investigated, in other words, with the goal of developing that self-reliance.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Obviously, all of this needs to be done on the basis of keeping the precepts, sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_04]: And so, how many so-called dhamma teachers actually have true self-reliance as a goal in their teaching?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, one of the criteria you can start seeing then, where does this teaching lead.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have another question.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, go ahead.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the gradual training, all the way up to jhāna, the jhāna would be the right meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in that gradual training, it doesn't exactly express, he achieves right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the gradual training, it brings about jhāna, but it doesn't explicitly mention right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: But right view is a prerequisite for jhāna, as I understand.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, usually the gradual
[SPEAKER_05]: Gradual training is taught to the monks.
[SPEAKER_05]: They are the ones that undertook the training.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, generally, unless it's... it's the other way around.
[SPEAKER_05]: When Buddha is talking to the monks, unless it's clearly stated that the monk does not have the right view, they would have the right view.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, in all bhikkhus, and bhikkhus this, bhikkhus you should contemplate this, it's already presupposed that they understood what the practice is.
[SPEAKER_05]: Otherwise, the Buddha wouldn't be talking on the level as if they already know what the practice is, and then encouraging them further.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, there were instances when some of the bhikkhus were not, didn't even have the right view, and those suttas, they would... it clearly states it.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then, they would, usually, at the end of that sutta, get the right view, and so on.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, eh... Having said that, you don't have... technically, you don't have to have the right view to have jhāna.
[SPEAKER_05]: You just need to be thoroughly withdrawn, mind dried up from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, but again, any...
[SPEAKER_05]: Any instruction, any notion, any contemplation that you might do that would result in that, today is known on account of the dhamma and the suttas.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it would be highly unlikely that you would be able to free your mind from sensuality, overcome it in jhāna, and not understand other much kind of lower aspects of the... from the suttas, such as, you know, Four Noble Truths and so on.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it would be... it would be unlikely that you wouldn't get the right view.
[SPEAKER_05]: But, say, even again, theoretically, you still don't get the right view.
[SPEAKER_05]: If you had developed jhānas, it means your mind would have already been pure from all those pollutions.
[SPEAKER_05]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_05]: 95 percent, let's say, which means it would be much more likely, much easier to then get the right view, because there are less obstructions of obscuring it.
[SPEAKER_05]: There's a difference when the Buddha would say, some person has a lot of dust in their eyes, some person doesn't.
[SPEAKER_05]: In other words, some some some person's mind is much more developed, someone else's isn't, and they would need much more, like, instruction, repeated, and so on, and would take a lot longer for them to
[SPEAKER_05]: Together, I view.
[SPEAKER_05]: But if the mind is developed from the things that are obscuring this understanding, then, if you turn it directly towards the understanding, it won't take that much.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because, as I said, there's not much standing in the way.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you don't need to
[SPEAKER_02]: Wait to have the right view before starting the gradual training, as far as I understand.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, yeah, that's... you know, you... that... but by doing it, you... you... you actually have a chance to understand it, for what it is, and by doing so, you get the right view.
[SPEAKER_05]: But as long as that doesn't mean that
[SPEAKER_05]: People should be doing a technique that they think is the gradual training.
[SPEAKER_05]: They will then bring the pleasure of jhāna.
[SPEAKER_05]: They will then result in the right view, because that's seriously wrong view.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, in the process of doing the gradual training, you need to be uprooting your wrong views about where the practice is, the place of sensory strength and withdrawal, that self-transparency.
[SPEAKER_05]: So... And that's what I'm saying, like, if you start keeping the precepts rightly, not relying on
[SPEAKER_05]: The authority of a teacher, not relying even on a community, in that sense, or a tradition, but doing it internally, as your... as solely dependent on your determination, your upholding of that direction, it would be highly unlikely that you would remain non-transparent about your motives and expectations and other kind of views you might have.
[SPEAKER_05]: But usually, as I said, when people start their graduate training, they would take on the precepts on account of one of these factors, so that they don't have to think for themselves, or they don't have to doubt it, they don't have to second-guess it every day.
[SPEAKER_05]: And it's like, no, you do have to.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's kind of the point.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's how you realize the extent of the hindrances, of the doubt, of the mind, and so on.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, understanding how to do the gradual training rightly, see, that's already something that can be developed in people.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, it's not just you read these steps and do them, because each and one of those steps, there are layers you can peel off of until you do it rightly.
[SPEAKER_05]: In the beginning, it won't be correct, for sure, but...
[SPEAKER_05]: So, yeah, it doesn't mean you shouldn't try anything until you get the right view, but you need to recognize that whatever you try,
[SPEAKER_05]: Without the right view, well, it won't be right, for whatever reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: When I'm practicing, like, restraint, just in regards to non-activity, per se, meaning not trying to do anything, particularly out of any hindrance that might happen,
[SPEAKER_00]: I get maybe a point where it feels like any investigation I do is out of the desire to get rid of the doubt about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it just feels more pleasant to not think about it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, as I said, it's not like something you can just stick to one
[SPEAKER_05]: Just stick to one way.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, never, never, never act out.
[SPEAKER_05]: Never do this.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because, again, it depends on why you're doing it at a time.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, if it's too tight, you need to loosen it.
[SPEAKER_05]: If it's too loose, you need to tighten it.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, if you are actually preferring the pleasure of non-investigation, that's probably a good sign that you should start investigating.
[SPEAKER_05]: And even if your mind is coming out of desire, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because otherwise it would be pleasant.
[SPEAKER_05]: So you realize desire is where the pleasure is.
[SPEAKER_04]: Perhaps another factor in questioning the authenticity of a teacher or a teaching is
[SPEAKER_04]: To find out how prepared the teacher is to having discussions.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because somebody might say, no, this is my practice, this is my method, it's working for me, and based on that, they basically block everything else.
[SPEAKER_04]: But if there's no attitude to even be open to alternative views,
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, that's the... yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: People can be open to views, but no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_05]: Can you actually reason your position?
[SPEAKER_05]: Give arguments.
[SPEAKER_05]: Not just, like, I'm not hearing any of this.
[SPEAKER_05]: This is the way I did it.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Finished story.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, like, can... can you ask questions?
[SPEAKER_05]: Can you get the corresponding answer to what you asked?
[SPEAKER_05]: Not like a generic, whatever you asked, you just get, well, watch your nostrils, or chant this mantra, or let go.
[SPEAKER_05]: Every, everything, everything.
[SPEAKER_05]: Whoever comes, whichever does, it's just the same thing.
[SPEAKER_05]: Just let go.
[SPEAKER_05]: Just, just, yeah, just chant.
[SPEAKER_05]: Just, just sit cross-legged.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's, again, if, if, if that were the way out, well, surely we would have come across it in the suttas as, as a way out.
[SPEAKER_05]: But it was, like, quite... much more elaborate, much more layered, as I said before.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, eh... there is... there is definitely, actually, a factor you can... you can see, even on the basis of, eh... of someone else's instruction, whether it is just an enclosed kind of faith-based, just do this, or there is... there is some...
[SPEAKER_05]: Intellect behind it, so to speak, there is some reason in there, clear kind of reflection, that can then be, you know, shared, questioned, and so on, explained differently, and so on.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, that's definitely important, actually.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the suttas, you know, whoever will come to the Buddha with a question, sometimes even quite antagonistic, wanting to debase,
[SPEAKER_02]: He would never, would always be able to answer every question.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It was, you know, doesn't matter who, from what direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, apart those questions he refused to answer, but obviously, then he would give reasons for refusing to answer those questions.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like...
[SPEAKER_05]: The ones that are based on the wrong premise.
[SPEAKER_04]: And, sorry, and also the seclusion is a factor.
[SPEAKER_04]: There's this discourse where somebody approaches the Buddha and says, well, we have all these different wanderers and they have all these views.
[SPEAKER_04]: How can you now know which one is right?
[SPEAKER_04]: And then he does say, okay, one factor is, do these people actually practically delight in seclusion and not just hang out with other people the whole time?
[SPEAKER_04]: That's now another thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: So that's basically even regardless of... this might be a sort of lesser standard, but still, because of that factor is not there, it's very questionable whether there's sufficient strength in the mind to have the right kind of discernment.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's another factor.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'd say, maybe it's another factor thing to be aware of in this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Things that it's not... it's not necessarily just about, like,
[SPEAKER_02]: Choosing a particular teacher, you then say, oh yeah, now that's the one that I've settled on, and I'm fairly sure that that's... because that would be obviously making yourself dependent on this.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think you need to kind of keep in mind that the only way, really, that you'll have a criteria to know which teacher, if there even is one, for example, like you don't even need to take for granted that there is even one teacher out there who is
[SPEAKER_02]: Teaching the same thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: What needs to be the priority is that you yourself know what's right and what's wrong for yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, from that perspective, you would be able to be sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, this teaching, I'm sure, because I've really trained in it and I've verified it for myself, that I can see.
[SPEAKER_05]: What about if somebody can't help?
[SPEAKER_05]: They just can't help but say, well, this is my teacher.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm so inspired.
[SPEAKER_05]: What do they do?
[SPEAKER_05]: Do they go and find another one or what do they do?
[SPEAKER_05]: How do they deal with that?
[SPEAKER_05]: Because everything that this person says, everything just resonates.
[SPEAKER_05]: He's the right teacher and that's it.
[SPEAKER_05]: But, again,
[SPEAKER_05]: You don't know that, so what do you do in that occasion?
[SPEAKER_05]: How can you know whether your inspiration is right or wrong?
[SPEAKER_05]: I mean, you're factually inspired, you're factually uplifted, you factually find sense in what's being said.
[SPEAKER_05]: You just stop caring about anybody else, any other instruction.
[SPEAKER_05]: But how do you now not blind yourself with that?
[SPEAKER_05]: What do you do?
[SPEAKER_03]: Take the medicine from the doctor.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, yeah, take it on faith.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have to actually...
[SPEAKER_03]: Apply it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Apply it in the end.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah, okay, the application.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, yeah, that's...
[SPEAKER_03]: And recognize this blind faith, I mean, as a hindrance?
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, yeah, maybe not as a hindrance, but recognize it as a factor there, and then question that.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, so you don't have to deny it, or I must find another one, or I must undo the inspiration, but it's like, what is it that I'm finding inspiring?
[SPEAKER_05]: Is it stuff that is genuinely inspiring?
[SPEAKER_05]: You find, yeah, that's the right guy or something.
[SPEAKER_05]: But, or is it... no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_05]: Factually, on the basis of my previous practice and everything else, things that I said, that's what you find inspiring.
[SPEAKER_05]: Things that you're required to do as a practice, that's what you find inspiring, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I was... if it's... if it's that, as in, if it's genuinely things that
[SPEAKER_02]: If you have made you understood things that you didn't hear from anybody else, and that have actually made you see things in a different way, not just like, oh, this clicks with what I was already thinking, sort of thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, yeah, that's a kind of a fairly good criteria.
[SPEAKER_02]: But even then, I would say that it's still not... Yeah, you still have to do it.
[SPEAKER_05]: You still have to do it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: But it's like, so, you might have inspiration, and then you start questioning that.
[SPEAKER_05]: As to what is the basis for it, what's your motivation behind.
[SPEAKER_05]: See if you're afraid to question.
[SPEAKER_05]: What that teacher says.
[SPEAKER_05]: Not necessarily with him, if he's on the other side of the world, but with yourself.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's like, okay, you know, I got it now.
[SPEAKER_05]: I understand what he's saying.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's like this, it's like this, it's like this.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then, you come across the opposing view.
[SPEAKER_05]: Oh, is there a passionate reaction to that?
[SPEAKER_05]: Is there an upset?
[SPEAKER_05]: Is there a defense mechanism?
[SPEAKER_05]: In which case, again, it still does not necessarily mean you're wrong, but you need to recognize, yeah, but why?
[SPEAKER_05]: So, if, if, eh...
[SPEAKER_05]: It's a frightening view.
[SPEAKER_05]: The only reason I would be afraid or feel defensive is because I'm not entirely certain in what I think I understood.
[SPEAKER_05]: So then, you use that experience, pretty much, that occasion to...
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, so then, I need to recognize that
[SPEAKER_05]: I need to understand more of this.
[SPEAKER_05]: Or if there is no more in that teaching, then you realize, well, I need to then find a teaching that will be impervious to doubt.
[SPEAKER_05]: And even if I come across the opposing views, and so on, that will not be able to sort of immediately switch me into that mode of, oh, I must defend this or I'll just turn a blind eye, I won't think about it.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, intentionally,
[SPEAKER_05]: Sometimes, intentionally, you will have to bring up the doubt in regard to what you think you understood, and then feel the weight of it, and then, yeah, see if what you understood remains there.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, of course, at the same time, you know, when I say bring up the doubt, it doesn't mean, like, just start spinning out of control and kind of doubt, but bring it up and leave it there, and then see what understanding you have, and what aspects of it are you doubting,
[SPEAKER_05]: Is it the irrational just pressure of doubt, or there are genuinely things that lack in clarity?
[SPEAKER_05]: In which case, that clarity needs to be developed.
[SPEAKER_05]: And when there are no more things that lack in clarity, you just realize you're just going around repeating the same stuff, or in other words, answering the same things to the questions your own doubt is asking, then you recognize, okay, now this is just the the hindrance of doubt, just sort of acting for its own sake.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, then you stop until the mind comes down.
[SPEAKER_05]: But then you can bring it up again.
[SPEAKER_05]: If you're too calm or find pleasure, too much pleasure in not provoking these reflections, then you should do it in that sense.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Just to see if the the the the solid understanding of it is there and whether it would stand the test or not.
[SPEAKER_03]: But a lot of our discussion so far has been based on this premise that
[SPEAKER_03]: The emphasis is on understanding, which isn't necessarily the case for, I think, a lot of interpretations of the Buddha's teaching, where
[SPEAKER_05]: I mean... Oh, right, right, sure, yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, yeah, that's... as we said in the beginning, that will easily... there will be a criteria that will easily, sort of, remove a lot of things that are presented as the Buddha's teaching.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because, again, if they don't bring understanding and the clarity in regard to the nature of suffering, nature of dhamma, the escape, and so on,
[SPEAKER_05]: That's the sort of experience that will just occur to you on account of certain practices.
[SPEAKER_05]: You can pretty much safely dismiss that in the beginning right away.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which is difficult to see, I think, right?
[SPEAKER_05]: I mean, based on the predominance of, I mean, most Buddhism today, I would say.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, that's why we come back to that transparency and so on.
[SPEAKER_05]: If you just, whatever you found appealing, whatever you're doing, whatever your practice is, don't forget about your own motivation in regard to it and start questioning it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, why?
[SPEAKER_05]: And does it add up?
[SPEAKER_05]: And start learning the suttas?
[SPEAKER_05]: And when I say learning, I mean investigate the meaning, not just sort of memorize the Pali and the historiological context of the texts and stuff like that.
[SPEAKER_05]: No, the actual try to understand what's meant by those things said two and a half thousand years ago, what do they refer to here and now in this experience while I'm reading the suttas.
[SPEAKER_05]: Those are the general categories of the human mind, of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, they're there while you're reading about them, but you're not seeing them.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it has to be understood at an immediate level.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I suppose one reason why it's quite difficult...
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, it is difficult to start that process, because the suttas are very... when you first come to them,
[SPEAKER_03]: And, yeah, that investigation obviously then can lead you into then an understanding of why emphasis is on the body or conceiving or what does that mean?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: But also, again, in my experience now, one thing that's sort of almost always overlooked is the whom the suttas apply to.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's like, oh, do I even meet the prerequisites of a summoner?
[SPEAKER_05]: And I don't mean, like, am I formally ordained or something, but am I living, withdrawn, keeping the priesthood secluded?
[SPEAKER_05]: To what extent?
[SPEAKER_05]: Because that is kind of, as I said, the basic threshold that neither Buddha would teach or instruct.
[SPEAKER_05]: And, yeah, sure, you had cases of householders,
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, it was a different time.
[SPEAKER_05]: But even then, it was the same procedure, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_05]: He would first, gladdened in my eye, turn it away from sensuality and household worries.
[SPEAKER_05]: Then, when that mind is gladdened and sort of calmed, he would then talk about the perils of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because if he just talks about perils of sensuality right away, on a mind that's not even gladdened or composed to any extent, well, that's not going to be taken lightly.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, then you gladden the mind, then he would teach about the perils of sensuality and the value of escape.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then they would understand it.
[SPEAKER_05]: And sure, they might then choose to go back
[SPEAKER_05]: So, now, you don't have to Buddha.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, first, you need to, again, gladden the mind and withdraw your mind from household worries.
[SPEAKER_05]: Then, you have to start seeing the peril and contemplating, invoking the peril of sensuality, so that the mind turns away.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then, craving and vulnerable truths won't be that far away.
[SPEAKER_05]: But most people's attitude is just replace one thing with the other.
[SPEAKER_05]: And not really undo and then build up on top of that undoing, by undoing more and more and more.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that's really the problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: We were pointing out as well that in household... average householder's life... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: The access to sensuality, comfort...
[SPEAKER_05]: I mean, I bet kings back then did not live as comfortably and luxuriously as people today live, generally.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which means, when you pick up sutta, you're reading sutta with that sensuality.
[SPEAKER_05]: You are reading from a completely wrong place, as in, you're not even aware that it doesn't...
[SPEAKER_05]: So, again, you can start learning, sure, and then start undoing, peeling off these layers, as I said, but
[SPEAKER_05]: If you just ignore that whole situation you are in, your own situation, and then just go straight into, hmm, yeah, nāmarūpa and conceivings and mūlapariyāya sutta and this, it's like, it's just gonna be an abstract theory, which is exactly how it happens.
[SPEAKER_05]: You have PhDs in Buddhism, fluent in Pali and not even being able to keep the five precepts.
[SPEAKER_05]: Professors and people like that.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's like, you're just not dhamma.
[SPEAKER_05]: Even if it's just the the Pali you speak, it's not the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_05]: And even if technically somebody, one in thousand people, can become a sotāpanna, with very little sense restraint and so on, because they have so many other faculties developed, sure, but that's not the standard.
[SPEAKER_05]: That was not standard back then.
[SPEAKER_05]: And it's not standard today.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, celibacy is not the opposite of a household life.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's possible to be a householder and a celibate.
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's an easy mistake that is made, I've noticed, nowadays.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, well, it always goes in the kind of... monks have to be celibate, so... but I can't be a monk because of some practical reasons.
[SPEAKER_05]: I have a mother to support, a family, thus I don't have to be celibate.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's the that's the reasoning there.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: But it is still at the same time means because I can't be a monk, thus I don't have to be celibate, but I can still practice the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's a bit of a mixed up idea.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, so, like, again, a person can just... if you think, like, I don't...
[SPEAKER_05]: I can't be a monk, but at the same time, being celibate or keeping the eight precepts, something like that, well, that's not necessary, you know.
[SPEAKER_05]: You can practice dhamma by keeping the five precepts.
[SPEAKER_05]: Just ask yourself, what do you have to lose if you keep the eight precepts?
[SPEAKER_05]: Would that obscure the dhamma practice or would that enhance it?
[SPEAKER_05]: What do you have to lose?
[SPEAKER_05]: And when I say it pleases, that's really what it means.
[SPEAKER_05]: The extent of engagement with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_05]: The other ones, whether you eat at 12.45 or 9.30, it's pointless.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's just that don't overdo it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Don't indulge it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Same.
[SPEAKER_05]: Sleeping in higher luxurious places means... How you spend your days?
[SPEAKER_05]: You're just in this luxury and comfort, sleeping all the time, lazy, stretching around like a wild boar after the meal, as the Buddha says in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_05]: Or is it a simpler life whereby you don't overindulge in sleep, you don't overindulge in food, and you're celibate?
[SPEAKER_05]: That's the Eight Precepts.
[SPEAKER_05]: You're not beautifying yourself for the sake of it, but if you stink after work, yeah, put some deodorant on if you have to go among other people.
[SPEAKER_05]: You're not doing it for the wrong reasons.
[SPEAKER_05]: You're not doing it for beautification or attraction.
[SPEAKER_05]: You're just doing it so people don't complain and harass you, have a shower and so on.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, the point is, it all boils down to that, the third precepts and the level of withdrawal from sensual desires, sexual desires in particular.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, when eight precepts means basically celibate, that's the emphasis there.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's something I thought about before, in terms of that difference between the five precepts and the eight precepts.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just that it's not about, yeah, like you said, it's not about the specificity of the precepts, but the five precepts are more like things that are just always unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, like, it would be good for everybody to keep them, whether they want to practice the dharma or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whereas Eight Precepts is more on the level of just, okay, what's the kind of relatively bare minimum type of lifestyle that I can set up around myself, context for, that's suitable for being watchful with my intentions, being moderate in eating, being wakeful,
[SPEAKER_02]: Being, you know, having, putting all that effort in, so like, okay, I need to live simply, I need to just, you know, eat for the right reasons, can help to sometimes limit the time, you know, not just entertain myself with distractions, and obviously selflessness.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like,
[SPEAKER_05]: I mean, the monks used to... some of the monks who got pinned up at night, in the beginning, there was no... there was no stipulation there.
[SPEAKER_05]: Then there were lots of practical issues arising with that, you know.
[SPEAKER_05]: So then the Buddha said, I'll just do it between, like, the dawn and the noon.
[SPEAKER_05]: Do it at the right time, where, kind of, things are quiet, people are out, it's daylight, it's just safer.
[SPEAKER_05]: But then, even then, some monks would not eat just one meal a day.
[SPEAKER_05]: They would eat, during that period of time, they would eat
[SPEAKER_05]: Again, it's like, where's your intention behind all of that?
[SPEAKER_05]: Where's your motivation?
[SPEAKER_05]: And when you start getting the right context, you realize, again, keep the five precepts with celibacy.
[SPEAKER_05]: Why not do that?
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, sure, maybe the meal is served at your work at 4.30, whatever, in the evening.
[SPEAKER_05]: You can't... but fine, don't eat anything before, eat it there, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, you don't have to technically, then, follow these these guidelines, but just keep the five precepts, which, as we said before, it's the basic wholesome behavior, and then add celibacy to it, for the third precept.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, I think that, for many people, there will be
[SPEAKER_05]: Certainly enough to start in the right direction.
[SPEAKER_05]: They're developing transparency and so on.
[SPEAKER_05]: But if you can keep the the the celibacy precepts, you won't have a problem with not sleeping in a high luxurious sleeping place or eating one meal a day or something like that.
[SPEAKER_05]: None of that would be an issue.
[SPEAKER_05]: Perfumes?
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, who cares about it now?
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because it's really it all boils down to that one.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's the that's the main the main the main strength, the main pull, the main issue, the main obstacle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Regarding the pressure of sexuality, in this type of environment, or in other monastery environments I've been to, it seems like just the reduction in the sort of stimulus of what's happening around you, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: Reduces it, like, so much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, as soon as I go back, it's like, everything is like, it's like pressuring.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, it felt like, maybe for a certain extent of time, that that defilement had been, like, very easily been
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm back in the city environment and I'm walking in the street and I'm keeping my eyes downcast and everything is, you know, pressuring me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like as if I've lost progress, so to say.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, where is the... where is the development?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it to seclude yourself until essentially you're an anāgāmī in regards to... Well, the development is like in how
[SPEAKER_05]: How far you would act out, and if you're not acting out, the development will be on the level of how pressured you are, because that pressure would lessen with the time, with the understanding, with the contemplation of when you're not pressured, with truly understanding the pattern of sensuality, as we spoke before, debate, the dissatisfaction, and really cementing those contexts and that perspective.
[SPEAKER_05]: But
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, the unsuitable environment will still bombard your senses and that will always be a form of harassment.
[SPEAKER_05]: Now, for anāgāmī or an arahant, that harassment of his senses is not something that he can sort of act out of.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's just inconceivable, because the pedal of the bait has been completely shunned, understood, correctly abandoned.
[SPEAKER_05]: But they still feel the harassment.
[SPEAKER_05]: Their eyes are still harassed with a perception that wants to pervert itself, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_05]: The ugly wants you to see it as beautiful, and so on.
[SPEAKER_05]: There was at the Rathapala Sutta in Majjhima Nikaya where, you know, he was already, if not fully enlightened, he was already way beyond sensuality.
[SPEAKER_05]: When he went home and the father tried to entice him first with the wealth, got his wives to try and seduce him, and he says, stop harassing me.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, all this is harassment.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's not that he was like oblivious to what was happening, the significance of those acts, of seductive behavior, of the value of gold and so on, but he could not not see it for what it is.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, he told father off, told him to better to put a gold at the bottom of the river, because it would bring less suffering their way, and called his wives sisters, and they kind of got a bit upset and fainted or something.
[SPEAKER_05]: But, yeah, he was factually, like, I don't want to say annoyed in the terms of angry, but, yeah, his senses were being bombarded the same.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, that's why anāgāmī-ārahant would not be able to live... Well, we had anāgāmīs that lived household lives, but anāgāmī-ārahant would not be able to live a household life.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because, simply, why would he bear annoyance and harassment of the senses that have no desire towards those things?
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's just discomfort, basically.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's factually uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's exactly the bait.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, that's the progress.
[SPEAKER_05]: Not going in the direction of the bait, regardless of the discomfort.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then, yeah, sometimes you just have to avoid this conflict.
[SPEAKER_05]: If it's too much pressure, it's better to upgrade the environment where you won't be as pressured.
[SPEAKER_05]: But, yeah, then don't confuse that for progress.
[SPEAKER_05]: You still recognize that, well, but have I seen the peril, the danger, and, you know, vomited the kind of the desire out and so on, or am I just sheltered here?
[SPEAKER_05]: And that's something, if you're transparent, you know the answer, even without having to go back to the environment, they will provoke you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the bait is the pressure.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, the bait is the pleasure that you get if you give in to the pressure.
[SPEAKER_05]: The bait is hidden in the pleasure, let's say it like that.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, acting out towards it means...
[SPEAKER_03]: Biting, taking, taking up the bit.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the gratification, the danger.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it also could be the escape, when you understand it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, it's like putting honey on a razor blade.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then making it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, the poisonous drink, the simile of the sutras, eh?
[SPEAKER_05]: That's the... the subtlety of sensuality is the... it's the subtlety of debate.
[SPEAKER_05]: You don't really see it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Your senses do not perceive.
[SPEAKER_05]: Your eyes, ears, they don't see anything that's disagreeable and so on.
[SPEAKER_05]: But the mind is factually pressured by it.
[SPEAKER_05]: And if you, on that level, you discern debate.
[SPEAKER_05]: Then, you know that there is a poison in a drink that is otherwise undetectable by your senses.
[SPEAKER_05]: But now, the knowledge that it is poisonous, that... that cannot change.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, although you can't smell it, you can't smell the poison, you can't touch it, you can't see it, but you can know that it's there.
[SPEAKER_05]: And when you know that it's there, no amount of pressure will make you take that drink.
[SPEAKER_05]: When you fully discern that it is there, actually, you see it on that mental level.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because, as we said before, if it weren't, why does sensuality need to pressure you towards acting?
[SPEAKER_05]: If it's wholesome, if it's good, why does it need to bombard you and trick you and manipulate you and control you?
[SPEAKER_05]: Why does it have a nature of a trap?
[SPEAKER_05]: Why does, you know, like, if it's generally good, why is it set up in a way that I end up being trapped?
[SPEAKER_05]: And that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_05]: Like, really, you could recognize the pattern and you see, yeah, so this...
[SPEAKER_05]: I don't know the implications of this setup, but I know that it cannot be for my welfare.
[SPEAKER_05]: As the suttas would say, he knows that, like, a hunter does not set up a trap for a welfare of the deer.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, the monk reflects that anything that has a nature of a trap, hey, look,
[SPEAKER_05]: It cannot be for my welfare.
[SPEAKER_05]: I don't know who set it up, I don't know why, and I don't need to know.
[SPEAKER_05]: All I know is how to reckon as a trap when I see it, and not fall into it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of difficult to try to convince someone who is just... No, it's pointless.
[SPEAKER_05]: And I think you should try to convince people about it.
[SPEAKER_05]: You're devaluing the actual practice.
[SPEAKER_05]: If somebody needs convincing, they're not going to make the effort necessary for understanding.
[SPEAKER_05]: You need to meet the instruction halfway.
[SPEAKER_05]: If it's shoved down your throat and put on you, it's not... it's going to be seen as something completely different from what it actually is.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it's not obvious for everybody that sensuality is a danger.
[SPEAKER_05]: No, of course not.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, if it were obvious, we wouldn't need all the instruction to free ourselves from it.